I am Mistress Frieren's apprentice.
我是芙莉蓮大人的弟子
You pass.
你合格了
Next!
下一個！
ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田鐘人，作畫：阿部司）
Denken, the Imperial Mage.
宮廷魔法使，鄧肯
I know about you.
我對你這個人頗有了解
I am honored.
那真是老夫的榮幸
You worked your way up while serving in the military
儘管在軍隊效力，卻一路努力向上
and now you are a mage with the most authority in the northern lands.
如今是北方諸國中最具權勢的魔法使
Your inspirational story is famous.
你那激勵人心的事蹟遠近馳名
Honestly, I wish I had met you when you were young.
老實說，要是能見到 年輕時的你就好了
When you were young, hot-blooded,
那時的你年輕氣盛，血氣方剛
and full of ambition.
而且充滿雄心壯志
I have no interest in a dying flame.
我對強弩之末不感興趣
At least, that's what I thought…
至少我本來是這麼想的…
You changed your mind?
現在想法改變了嗎？
The moment you saw me, you thought about
你啊，看到我的瞬間就在想
how you would fight me, didn't you?
要怎麼跟我戰鬥了，對吧？
Just for a split second. I gave up right away.
只有一瞬間而已，馬上就放棄了
You pass. Your flame is still burning.
你合格了，看來你還有野心呢
Normal people wouldn't even think about fighting me.
一般人根本不會想要跟我戰鬥
Next.
下一位
You pass.
你合格了
But I haven't said anything yet.
可是我什麼都還沒說耶
Is a conversation necessary?
還有對話的必要嗎？
I guess you're right.
這麼說也對啦
Next.
下一位
You must be joking.
你別開玩笑了
What do you mean?
什麼意思？
This is a first-class mage exam, you know?
你知道這是一級魔法使選拔測驗吧？
What kind of idiot doesn't come to the exam even once?
一次都沒有出現在考場 這是哪來的笨蛋？
As you can see,
如你所見
I am here in the flesh as well,
我本人也到場了
to qualify as a participant--
缺席就不合格了…
During this entire exam,
整個考試過程中
your real body hasn't left your hometown, has it?
你的本體不曾離開過家鄉一步吧？
I bet you're leisurely enjoying teatime.
現在還很悠哉地在喝下午茶
That's surprising.
真令人意外
Even Übel didn't notice.
這點連尤蓓爾都沒能看出來
You have quite the audacity. You pass.
膽子還真大，你合格了
Next.
下一位
You're Wirbel, the captain of the Northern Magic Corps, right?
你是北部魔法隊隊長威亞貝爾吧？
Out of all the second-class mages I know,
在所有我認識的二級魔法使之中
you are the most equipped for combat.
你是最為善戰的一個
The moment you saw me,
你看到我的那一刻
you realized that you couldn't win against me.
就知道自己打不過我了
But that conclusion wasn't made out of fear.
但這並非是出於恐懼而下的結論
If I was a fool who'd start an unwinnable fight,
如果我是個明知打不過 還要開戰的蠢蛋
I wouldn't be a second-class mage.
就不會成為二級魔法使了吧
That's true.
說得也對
Tell me a spell you like.
告訴我你喜歡的魔法
Magic is a killing tool.
魔法這種東西就是殺人工具
I don't like or hate any of them.
有什麼好喜歡或討厭的？
You pass.
合格了
Next.
下一位
What did you think when you saw me?
你看到我的時候在想什麼？
Um… I thought you were small and adorable.
這個嘛，我覺得您小小一隻很可愛
What is wrong with these examinees this year?
今年的考生是怎麼了？
You pass.
你合格了
Sense,
冉則
I apologize.
抱歉了
This year's group was particularly talented.
今年確實收穫不少有才能的人
I failed…
我沒過…
There's always next time.
總會有下次機會嘛
Stop following me.
別再跟著我了
Three years from now, huh?
三年後嗎？
Mistress Frieren, I passed.
芙莉蓮大人，我合格了
Good job.
做得好
Frieren.
芙莉蓮
We were able to make it this far thanks to you two.
多虧有兩位幫忙 我們才能走到這一步
Now I can visit the cemetery in my hometown.
這樣老夫也可以回故鄉掃墓了
I see.
這樣啊
Come on, Fern.
喂，費倫
Can you hurry up?
你還沒選好嗎？
-I'll go with this. -This one.
-我選這… -就是這個
Eat as much as you want.
想吃多少儘管吃
When I was young,
老夫年輕的時候
I rarely had the chance to eat sweet things.
可沒什麼機會可以吃甜的東西
Thank you very much.
真的很謝謝您
Why am I here?
這是…什麼情況？
Eat up, young'un.
吃吧，小夥子
Thanks, old man.
謝謝你，老爺爺
Who is he?
他是誰啊？
He's Master Denken, an Imperial Mage.
他是宮廷魔法使，鄧肯大人
An Imperial Mage, huh?
宮廷魔法使嗎？
You mean he's a noble?!
那不就是貴族嗎？
Um, I'm sorry I spoke to you informally.
那個…對不起，我剛剛說話多有冒犯
It's fine.
沒關係
I came to this town as nothing but a regular mage.
老夫純粹是以一般魔法使的身分 來到這座城鎮的
But I can't let you treat me, when I'm a complete stranger.
但我跟您素昧平生 怎麼能讓您請客呢？
I don't have anything else to spend my money on.
反正也沒有別的地方可以花錢了
That can't be true.
不可能吧
Yeah, what about your grandchildren?
是啊，可以用在孫子身上吧？
I don't have any children or grandchildren.
老夫膝下無子，也沒有孫輩
When I was in my mid-twenties, my wife died.
內人在老夫二十多歲時就撒手人寰
She always had health problems.
她身體狀況一直都不好
She was the daughter of a noble from
她原本是北部高原
a remote area in the Northern Plateau, who lost in a political struggle.
政治鬥爭失勢的邊境貴族之女
At the time, I needed both wealth and power.
當時，老夫需要財富也需要權勢
Those were the only things I could think of that could save her.
那是老夫想得到的 唯一能夠救她的辦法
But Serie established
但是賽莉耶建立了
the Continental Magic Association with the promise
大陸魔法協會，並承諾
of granting people a privilege shortly after my wife died.
授予人們特權時 那時內人才剛剛過世
I've never felt as helpless as I did then.
那一刻老夫生平第一次感到絕望
It's so ironic.
實在是諷刺啊
Now, I have enough power to move entire nations.
如今老夫卻已經擁有 能夠動搖整個國家的權勢
Fern,
費倫
to me, magic was nothing but
魔法對老夫而言不過就是
a tool to use for political strife.
政治鬥爭的工具罷了
Will you please tell Frieren
請你轉告芙莉蓮一句話，好嗎？
that for the first time in a while, I was reminded
老夫睽違多時，再度感受到
of the fact that magic can be fun.
魔法其實很有趣這件事
I became a mage because I wanted to be like Frieren,
當年老夫是因為憧憬 勇者一行人當中的
the mage in the party of heroes.
魔法使芙莉蓮才成為魔法使的
Please tell her that yourself.
請親自告訴她吧
I'm sure Mistress Frieren would appreciate that.
相信芙莉蓮大人聽到一定會很高興
That's true.
說得對呢
I'll do that.
老夫會的
As expected of Äußerst, the city of magic.
真不愧是魔法之都歐伊沙斯特
I was able to buy so many great grimoires.
買到很多超棒的魔導書呢
Hey, old lady.
喂，老婆婆
Do they all need to go into this basket?
需要通通裝進這個籃子嗎？
I can't believe you ignored that.
真不敢相信你居然視而不見
I thought about helping for a second.
我也有稍微想過要去幫忙
Just for a second, huh?
只是稍微想過嗎？
I'm so surprised.
真是令人意外
I thought a party member of Himmel the Hero would be…
我還以為勇者欣梅爾的夥伴會…
A party member of Himmel would be what?
欣梅爾的夥伴會怎樣？
Speaking of being surprised, I was too.
我才更意外呢
I heard you tried to kill Fern's party in the first stage.
聽說你在第一階段考試時 打算殺掉費倫那支小隊
She was complaining about you.
她可是抱怨過了
She said you seem like the type who'd kick a dog.
她說你看起來就像 會亂踢無辜小狗的人
I get that often.
我常聽人這麼說我呢
I was only trying to scare them.
我只不過是想威嚇對方而已
Although,
不過呢
I would've done the world a favor if I had killed one of them.
真的有個除掉就能造福世界的人呢
I will do anything in order to protect my hometown.
只要能守護家鄉，要我做什麼都可以
I wanted to become a first-class mage
之所以想成為一級魔法使
for the privilege of being granted a spell of my choice.
也是為了可以學到想要的魔法的特權
If I get a hold of a strong spell,
要是能學到威力強大的魔法
I'll be able to kill that many more demons.
就可以幹掉超多魔族吧
But even when it has nothing to do with demons,
不過，就算與幹掉魔族無關
I try to help anyone who is in need as much as I can.
我還是會盡可能幫助有需要的人
Why?
為什麼？
My hometown is in a remote area in the north.
我的故鄉在北方邊境
The people there know countless stories of Himmel the Hero.
那裡的人知道不少勇者欣梅爾的事蹟
From the conquest of the Thousand-Mirror Tower
攻克千鏡之塔
to the battles against Böse the Immortal and the hell emperor dragon.
對戰七崩賢不死的貝傑還有皇獄龍
When I was a kid, I loved those tales of adventures.
當時還是小鬼的我 超愛聽這些傳奇的冒險故事
But the older ones in the village never talked about those stories.
但是村裡的爺爺奶奶們 卻很少提及這樣的故事
"He took down a monster who attacked the village."
“他打倒了襲擊村子的魔物”
"He escorted a merchant." Those were their stories.
“他當過商人的護衛”，都是這些
The worst story was about how he simply transported goods.
更過分的還有要他去搬貨
They weren't exciting at all.
一點也不刺激
"What a boring story." That's what I thought.
“這些故事有夠無聊” 我當時就是這麼想的
But the older ones in the village
但是村裡的爺爺奶奶們
looked so happy as they all shared stories like that.
在講這些雞毛蒜皮的小事時 看起來卻非常開心
After Himmel the Hero died
勇者欣梅爾過世以後
and the remaining demons began to run amok, it all made sense.
魔族殘黨又開始興風作浪，我就懂了
In reality,
的確
the Thousand-Mirror Tower, Böse, the hell emperor dragon,
千鏡之塔也好 貝傑也好，還有皇獄龍也是
and even the Demon King were irrelevant to my village.
就連魔王也跟我的村子沒半點關係
Everyone had their hands full just trying to protect their daily lives.
大家光是要守住日常生活 就已經忙不過來了
If Himmel the Hero hadn't come to my village,
要是勇者欣梅爾沒來過我的村子
it wouldn't have been around to see a peaceful world.
那裡大概沒機會 倖存到世界和平的時候吧
I see. What is your point?
是喔，所以你想表達什麼？
What brought me to where I am right now
讓我走到今天這一步的
is Himmel the Hero's trivial tales of adventures.
正是勇者欣梅爾 那些雞毛蒜皮的冒險故事啊
That's all I wanted to say.
我想說的話就這些了
I guess I was talking for too long.
似乎是講太久了
As it turns out, I'm going to go back with those two.
到頭來我還是要 跟那兩個傢伙一起回去呢
Frieren, you should cherish the people you encounter.
芙莉蓮，好好珍惜邂逅的人吧
Death isn't the only thing that separates people forever.
能讓人永別一生的並不只有死亡
But I'm sure you're fully aware of that.
相信你已經了然於胸了吧
Frieren, can't you use magic to
芙莉蓮，你不能用魔法
carry them one by one to the other side?
把牠們一個個運到另一邊嗎？
Then I'll be left alone on this side.
那我不就一個人被留在這邊了嗎？
Himmel,
欣梅爾
we can't waste any time in taking down the Demon King.
我們要打敗魔王 不能在這裡浪費時間
Why do we have to do such trivial acts of kindness?
為什麼非得做這些沒意義的小善行？
True, it's a trivial act of kindness.
的確是沒意義的小善行
Doing things like this won't change the world, I'm sure.
做這種事肯定改變不了世界
But I have no intention
但我無意
of ignoring people who are within reach, when they need help.
在力所能及的範圍內 忽視需要幫助的人
Don't worry, Himmel.
不要緊的，欣梅爾
The world is changing, for sure.
世界一定正在改變
We're going to be awarded our privilege tonight.
今晚會有授予特權的儀式
Apparently, we can bring companions.
據說可以攜帶同伴前往
So why don't we all go together?
機會難得，要不要大家一起去？
She looks really reluctant.
那張臉看起來很不情願呢
Um, I was told that I can bring a companion though.
那個，之前不是說過 可以帶一名同伴嗎？
I'm very sorry.
真的很抱歉
Mistress Serie has informed us that Mistress Frieren is banned.
賽莉耶大人有令 禁止芙莉蓮大人入內
She does not want you to enter
未來的一千年內
any Continental Magic Association facility for another 1000 years.
也禁止她出入 任何大陸魔法協會的機構
What did Mistress Frieren do to deserve this treatment?
芙莉蓮大人 究竟做了什麼才這樣對她？
It can't be helped.
這也是沒辦法的事
I upset Serie, after all.
畢竟是我惹賽莉耶生氣的
She's so childish, isn't she?
真是的，她真的好幼稚，對吧？
Well, it's not like I came here because I wanted to anyway.
反正我也不是想來才來的
I'll be waiting outside.
我去外面等
I'll wait outside too.
那我也去外面等
Hey!
喂！
That's the evening bell.
是傍晚的鐘聲
They should be done awarding the privileges soon.
特權應該很快就會授予完畢了
Yeah.
是啊
A first-class mage…
一級魔法使…
The highest rank of mages that less than 50 people in the world claim to be.
全世界不到五十人 魔法使的最高位階啊
Fern has come a long way.
費倫真的大有進步呢
In this generation,
在這個時代
Fern will probably become a mage more famous than me.
費倫一定會成為比我還有名的魔法使
Frieren…
芙莉蓮…
Isn't that great?
真令人高興
Yeah, it is.
就是說啊
Mistress Frieren.
芙莉蓮大人
Who is that?
那是誰？
Someone from the Continental Magic Association.
大陸魔法協會的人
I am Lernen, a first-class mage.
我是一級魔法使，列魯寧
I'm one of Mistress Serie's apprentices.
是賽莉耶大人門下的弟子之一
It seems that Mistress Serie has caused you trouble.
看來賽莉耶大人給你們添麻煩了
It's fine.
沒關係
She's always been this way.
她打從以前就是這樣
What's wrong, Frieren?
怎麼了，芙莉蓮？
You see it, don't you?
你果然看得到吧？
The instability of my mana.
我的魔力晃動
You're extremely skilled.
真是實力超群呢
Which is surprising to see in an era of peace.
這種和平時代竟有這種人才 真令人意外
I agree.
確實如此
I am an outdated mage who only knows how to fight.
我只會戰鬥，是個生錯時代的魔法使
Mistress Serie tells me all the time,
賽莉耶大人也總是這麼說
that if I was born during the war against the Demon King's army,
她說我要是生在對抗魔王軍的時代
I would have gone down in history
一定會跟其他英雄
along with other famous heroes.
一起名垂青史
I see. So what do you want from me?
是嗎？那你找我想做什麼呢？
Among Mistress Serie's apprentices,
在賽莉耶大人的弟子中
the only one who has gone down in history
唯一一位留名青史的魔法使
is the Great Mage Flamme, who is now treated like a mythical being.
就是如今有如神話般存在的 大魔法使弗蘭梅
If I die of old age,
哪天我老死了
Mistress Serie will lose one more testament to her existence.
見證賽莉耶大人存在的人 就又少了一個
I don't want to leave her
我不希望在未來
all alone, with nothing in the future.
留下那位大人孤身一人
I want to leave her with something,
我想留點什麼給那位大人
even if that is the notoriety of killing Mistress Frieren, the legendary mage.
就算要背負殺害傳奇魔法使 芙莉蓮大人的惡名也沒關係
I challenge you to a duel, Mistress Frieren.
能與我一較高下嗎，芙莉蓮大人？
I will not duel you. It's a waste of time.
我不會跟你打的，這根本浪費時間
Jeez…
真是的…
Mages who only know how to fight
只知道戰鬥的魔法使
are never good at communicating their feelings.
都不擅長表達自己的情感呢
There's no need to go down in history.
根本沒必要留名青史
Serie will remember.
賽莉耶會好好記住你的
One more thing before I go…
走之前我還想問一件事
This flower garden was made using magic.
這個花園是用魔法製造出來的吧
What about that?
那有怎麼樣嗎？
It was Master's favorite spell.
那是師父最喜歡的魔法
Didn't you call it a "stupid spell"?
你不是說這個魔法很無聊嗎？
Honestly, Flamme was a failure.
老實說，弗蘭梅是個失敗品
Despite having as much talent as she did,
儘管她如此才華過人
she couldn't reach my level.
卻無法達到我的程度
After her, I took in lots of apprentices.
我在她之後又收了很多徒弟
Almost all of them died before me, without coming even close to my level.
其中大多數人都學不到什麼就走了
But it's strange.
可是很不可思議
Even though I took them in on a whim,
儘管我是一時興起才收他們為徒
I can clearly remember each of their
卻能清楚記得他們
personalities and their favorite spells.
每個人的個性還有最愛的魔法
Frieren, for some reason, I've never regretted
芙莉蓮，不知為何，我連一次
taking an apprentice even once.
也沒後悔過曾經收人為徒
Even if they weren't able to go down in history.
儘管他們無法留名青史
She can't even express her honest feelings to her apprentice.
連對自己的弟子 都不能誠實地表達情感嗎？
She's really such a child.
還真是有夠孩子氣
Mistress Frieren.
芙莉蓮大人
They've finished awarding privileges.
特權授予儀式結束了
Then let's go.
那我們走吧
Mistress Frieren, what happened to your shoulder?
芙莉蓮大人，您的肩膀怎麼了？
I need to get it healed at the church.
我得去教堂治療一下
I hope they're open.
但願他們還沒關門
We really are bad at communicating.
真的很不會說話呢
You and I both.
你跟我都是
Stark, what kind of game do you want to play today?
修塔爾克，你今天想玩什麼遊戲？
Sorry, I can't play with you guys today.
抱歉啦，大哥哥今天不能跟你們玩喔
Stark, did you eat breakfast?
修塔爾克，早餐吃了沒有？
I already did.
吃過了
Oh, thanks!
謝謝！
The path to strength is complex and dangerous.
武學之路複雜又凶險
I wish you well.
你要保重啊
Thanks.
謝謝
It's time to say goodbye to Äußerst.
這下要跟歐伊沙斯特道別了呢
Stark, everyone seems to love you wherever you go.
修塔爾克大人到哪都很受歡迎呢
You think so?
是嗎？
By the way, what kind of spell did you receive yesterday?
話說回來，費倫 昨天她授予你什麼魔法？
Can't you tell?
看不出來嗎？
Your clothes are clean.
衣服變乾淨了
And have a floral scent.
而且還有股花香
Don't tell me…
這個難道是…
It's the spell to make clothes clean and spotless.
是將衣服的髒汙澈底清除的魔法
This will make doing laundry so easy.
這樣洗衣服就能輕鬆多了
Serie lives up to her name as the living grimoire.
真不愧是賽莉耶 號稱活生生的魔導書
That's a legendary spell that is said to have existed in mythical times.
據說這可是神話時代中的傳奇魔法呢
Way to go, Fern.
太棒了，費倫
You truly are my apprentice.
這樣才是我的弟子嘛
Of course, I am, Mistress Frieren.
那是當然的了，芙莉蓮大人
Mistress Serie looked very reluctant though.
只不過賽莉耶大人看起來很不情願
You must be insane.
你是瘋了吧
I can imagine. Serves her right.
我想也是，她活該
Oh, she's here.
來了
Frieren!
芙莉蓮！
Thanks for everything.
真的很謝謝你
We failed this time,
我們這次都沒合格
but we'll try again in three years.
三年之後要再努力一次
Yeah? I'm glad.
這樣嗎？那很好啊
-It was fun. -Take care.
-跟你在一起很開心 -要保重喔
-See you. -Yeah, see you.
-那麼再見了 -嗯，再見
It's just like the time with Sein.
就跟贊恩大人分別的時候一樣
You part ways with people so easily.
您道別的方式都很瀟灑呢
She was this way with Kraft too.
對克拉福特也是啊
Himmel,
欣梅爾你啊
you part ways with people so easily, don't you?
跟別人道別都很瀟灑，對吧？
Is that weird?
這樣很奇怪嗎？
Well, knowing you, it's surprising.
正因為認識你才感到意外啊
Even if it was just a job, we did travel together for two weeks, after all.
雖然只是工作 但好歹也相處了兩星期
Plus, he drank with us
說起來那傢伙幾乎
almost every night and was so--
每天晚上都跟我們喝酒，而且很…
You corrupt priest…
酒肉僧侶…
I guess so.
說得也是
But as long as our journey continues, we can always meet again.
但只要我們繼續這趟旅途 總有一天會再相見吧
Tearful goodbyes don't suit us.
淚眼相送不太適合我們
After all, it'll be embarrassing when we meet again.
畢竟再相見時，這樣會不好意思吧
It'll be embarrassing when we meet again.
不然再相見時會不好意思吧
-Huh?
-什麼？
What do you mean?
這是什麼回答啊？
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻譯：洪貞韻